<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <caution>
    <para>
      You are looking at the documentation for a version of PHPUnit that is no
      longer supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      The documentation for the current version of PHPUnit can be found
      <ulink url="../../current/en/index.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </caution>

  <para>
    For a very long time my answer to the question "When will you write
    documentation for PHPUnit?" has been "You do not need documentation for
    PHPUnit. Just read the documentation for JUnit or a buy a book on JUnit
    and adapt the code examples from Java and JUnit to PHP and PHPUnit."
    When I mentioned this to Barbara Weiss and Alexandra Follenius from the
    O'Reilly Germany office, they encouraged me to think it over and
    write a book that would serve as the documentation for PHPUnit.
  </para>

  <section id="preface.requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      The topic of this book is PHPUnit, an open source framework for test-driven
      development with the PHP programming language. This edition covers Version
      2.3 of PHPUnit. Most of the examples should work, however, with PHPUnit
      versions 2.0-2.2. The "PHPUnit for PHP 4" section, later in this book,
      covers the older, no longer actively developed version of PHPUnit for
      PHP 4.
    </para>

    <para>
      The reader should have a good understanding of object-oriented
      programming with PHP 5. To German readers I can recommend my own book on
      PHP 5, <xref linkend="Bergmann2005" />, as an introduction to
      object-oriented programming with PHP 5. A good English book on the subject
      is <xref linkend="GuBaRe2005" /> by Andi Gutmans, Stig Bakken, and Derick
      Rethans.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="preface.license">
    <title>This Book Is Free</title>

    <para>
      This book is available under the Creative Commons Attribution License. You
      will always find the latest version of this book on its website at
      <uri>http://www.phpunit.de/pocket_guide/</uri>.
      You may distribute and make changes to this book however you wish. Of
      course, rather than distribute your own private version of the book,
      I would prefer you send feedback and patches to
      <email>sb@sebastian-bergmann.de</email>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="preface.conventions">
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para>
      The following is a list of typographical conventions used in this book:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Italic</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates new terms, URLs, email addresses, filenames, file
            extensions, pathnames, directories, and Unix utilities.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>Constant width</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates commands, options, switches, variables, functions,
            classes, namespaces, methods, modules, parameters, values,
            objects, the contents of files, or the output from commands.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><userinput>Constant width bold</userinput></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally
            by the user.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied values.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>
      You should pay special attention to notes set apart from the text
      with the following styles:
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        This is a tip, suggestion, or general note. It contains useful
        supplementary information about the topic at hand.
      </para>
    </note>

    <warning>
      <para>
        This is a warning or note of caution.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </section>

  <section id="preface.acknowledgements">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>
      I would like to thank Kent Beck and Erich Gamma for JUnit and the
      inspiration to write PHPUnit. I would also like to thank Kent Beck for
      his "JUnit Pocket Guide" <xref linkend="Beck2004" />, which sparked the
      idea for this book. I would like to thank Allison Randal, Alexandra
      Follenius, and Barbara Weiss for sponsoring this book at O'Reilly.
    </para>

    <para>
      I would like to thank Andi Gutmans, Zeev Suraski, and Marcus Börger
      for their work on the Zend Engine 2, the core of PHP 5. I would like to
      thank Derick Rethans for Xdebug, the PHP extension that makes PHPUnit's
      Code Coverage functionality possible. Finally, I would like to thank
      Michiel Rook, who wrote the PHPUnit tasks for Phing.
    </para>
  </section>
</preface>
