<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<chapter id="goals">
  <title>PHPUnit's Goals</title>

  <caution>
    <para>
      You are looking at the documentation for a version of PHPUnit that is no
      longer supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      The documentation for the current version of PHPUnit can be found
      <ulink url="../../current/en/index.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </caution>

  <para>
    So far, we only have two tests for the <literal>array</literal> built-in
    and the <literal>sizeof()</literal> function. When we start to test the
    numerous <literal>array_*()</literal> functions PHP offers, we will need
    to write a test for each of them. We could write the infrastructure for
    all these tests from scratch. However, it is much better to write a
    testing infrastructure once and then write only the unique parts of each
    test. PHPUnit is such an infrastructure.
  </para>

  <para>
    <xref linkend="goals.examples.ArrayTest.php" /> shows how we have to
    rewrite our two tests from
    <xref linkend="automating-tests.examples.array-test4.php" /> so that we
    can use them with PHPUnit.
  </para>

  <example id="goals.examples.ArrayTest.php">
    <title>Testing Array and sizeof() with PHPUnit</title>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
require_once 'PHPUnit2/Framework/TestCase.php';

class ArrayTest extends PHPUnit2_Framework_TestCase {
    public function testNewArrayIsEmpty() {
        // Create the Array fixture.
        $fixture = array();

        // Assert that the size of the Array fixture is 0.
        $this->assertEquals(0, sizeof($fixture));
    }

    public function testArrayContainsAnElement() {
        // Create the Array fixture.
        $fixture = array();

        // Add an element to the Array fixture.
        $fixture[] = 'Element';

        // Assert that the size of the Array fixture is 1.
        $this->assertEquals(1, sizeof($fixture));
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>
    <indexterm><primary>PHPUnit2_Framework_TestCase</primary></indexterm>

    <xref linkend="goals.examples.ArrayTest.php" /> shows the basic steps
    for writing tests with PHPUnit:
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>The tests for a class <literal>Class</literal> go into a class <literal>ClassTest</literal>.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><literal>ClassTest</literal> inherits (most of the time) from <literal>PHPUnit2_Framework_TestCase</literal>.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The tests are public methods that expect no parameters and are named <literal>test*</literal>.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Inside the test methods, assertion methods such as <literal>assertEquals()</literal> (see <xref linkend="api.assert.tables.assertions" />) are used to assert that an actual value matches an expected value.</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
    A framework such as PHPUnit has to resolve a set of constraints, some of
    which seem always to conflict with each other. Simultaneously, tests
    should be:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Easy to learn to write.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If it's hard to learn how to write tests, developers will not learn
          to write them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Easy to write.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If tests are not easy to write, developers will not write them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Easy to read.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Test code should contain no extraneous overhead so that the test
          itself does not get lost in noise that surrounds it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Easy to execute.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The tests should run at the touch of a button and present their
          results in a clear and unambiguous format.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Quick to execute.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tests should run fast so so they can be run hundreds or thousands
          of times a day.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Isolated.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The tests should not affect each other. If the order in which the
          tests are run changes, the results of the tests should not change.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Composable.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We should be able to run any number or combination of tests together.
          This is a corollary of isolation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    There are two main clashes between these constraints:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Easy to learn to write versus easy to write.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tests do not generally require all the flexibility of a programming
          language. Many testing tools provide their own scripting language
          that only includes the minimum necessary features for writing tests.
          The resulting tests are easy to read and write because they have no
          noise to distract you from the content of the tests. However,
          learning yet another programming language and set of programming
          tools is inconvenient and clutters the mind.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Isolated versus quick to execute.</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you want the results of one test to have no effect on the results
          of another test, each test should create the full state of the world
          before it begins to execute and return the world to its original
          state when it finishes. However, setting up the world can take a
          long time: for example connecting to a database and initializing it
          to a known state using realistic data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    PHPUnit attempts to resolve these conflicts by using PHP as the testing
    language. Sometimes the full power of PHP is overkill for writing little
    straight-line tests, but by using PHP we leverage all the experience and
    tools programmers already have in place. Since we are trying to convince
    reluctant testers, lowering the barrier to writing those initial tests
    is particularly important.
  </para>

  <para>
    PHPUnit errs on the side of isolation over quick execution. Isolated
    tests are valuable because they provide high-quality feedback. You do
    not get a report with a bunch of test failures, which were really caused
    because one test at the beginning of the suite failed and left the world
    messed up for the rest of the tests. This orientation towards isolated
    tests encourages designs with a large number of simple objects. Each
    object can be tested quickly in isolation. The result is better designs
    <emphasis>and</emphasis> faster tests.
  </para>

  <para>
    PHPUnit assumes that most tests succeed and it is not worth reporting
    the details of successful tests. When a test fails, that fact is worth
    noting and reporting. The vast majority of tests should succeed and are
    not worth commenting on except to count the number of tests that run.
    This is an assumption that is really built into the reporting classes,
    and not into the core of PHPUnit. When the results of a test run are
    reported, you see how many tests were executed, but you only see details
    for those that failed.
  </para>

  <para>
    Tests are expected to be fine-grained, testing one aspect of one object.
    Hence, the first time a test fails, execution of the test halts, and
    PHPUnit reports the failure. It is an art to test by running in many
    small tests. Fine-grained tests improve the overall design of the system.
  </para>

  <para>
    When you test an object with PHPUnit, you do so only through the
    object's public interface. Testing based only on publicly visible
    behaviour encourages you to confront and solve difficult design problems
    earlier, before the results of poor design can infect large parts of the
    system.
  </para>
</chapter>
