<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<chapter id="stubs">
  <title>Stubs</title>

  <caution>
    <para>
      You are looking at the documentation for a version of PHPUnit that is no
      longer supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      The documentation for the current version of PHPUnit can be found
      <ulink url="../../current/en/index.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </caution>

  <para>
    <indexterm><primary>Stubs</primary></indexterm>

    Tests that only test one thing are more informative than tests where
    failure can come from many sources. How can you isolate your tests from
    external influences? Simply put, by replacing the expensive, messy,
    unreliable, slow, complicated resources with stubs made from plain PHP
    objects. For example, you can implement what is in reality a complicated
    computation by returning a constant, at least for the purposes of a
    single test.
  </para>

  <para>
    <indexterm><primary>PHPUnit2_Extensions_TestSetup</primary></indexterm>

    Stubs solve the problem of allocating expensive external resources.
    For example, sharing a resource, such as a database connection, between
    tests by using the <literal>PHPUnit2_Extensions_TestSetup</literal>
    decorator helps, but not using the database for the purposes of the tests
    at all is even better.
  </para>

  <para>
    Design improvement is one effect of using stubs. Widely used resources
    are accessed through a single façade, so you can easily replace the
    resource with the stub. For example, instead of having direct database
    calls scattered throughout the code, you have a single
    <literal>Database</literal> object, an implementor of the
    <literal>IDatabase</literal> interface. Then, you can create a stub
    implementation of <literal>IDatabase</literal> and use it for your
    tests. You can even create an option for running the tests with the
    stub database or the real database, so you can use your tests for both
    local testing during development and integration testing with the real
    database.
  </para>

  <para>
    Functionality that needs to be stubbed out tends to cluster in the same
    object, improving cohesion. By presenting the functionality with a
    single, coherent interface, you reduce the coupling with the rest of the
    system.
  </para>

  <section id="stubs.self-shunting">
    <title>Self-Shunting</title>

    <para>
      <indexterm><primary>Self Shunt Pattern</primary></indexterm>

      Sometimes you need to check that an object has been called correctly. You
      can create a complete stub of the object to be called, but that can make
      it inconvenient to check for correct results. A simpler solution is to
      apply the <emphasis>Self Shunt Pattern</emphasis> and use the test-case
      object itself as a stub. The term self-shunting is taken from the medical
      practice of installing a tube that takes blood from an artery and returns
      it to a vein to provide a convenient place for injecting drugs.
    </para>

    <para>
      <indexterm><primary>Observer Pattern</primary></indexterm>

      Here is an example: suppose we want to test that the correct method is
      called on an object that observes another object. First, we make our
      test-case class an implementor of <literal>Observer</literal>:
<programlisting>class ObserverTest extends PHPUnit2_Framework_TestCase implements Observer {
}</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Next, we implement the one <literal>Observer</literal> method,
      <literal>update()</literal>, to check that it is called when the state
      of the observed <literal>Subject</literal> object changes:
<programlisting>public $wasCalled = FALSE;

public function update(Subject $subject) {
    $this->wasCalled = TRUE;
}</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Now, we can write our test. We create a new <literal>Subject</literal>
      object and attach the test object to it as an observer. When the state
      of the <literal>Subject</literal> changes -- for instance, by calling its
      <literal>doSomething()</literal> method -- the <literal>Subject</literal>
      object has to call the <literal>update()</literal> method on all objects
      that are registered as observers. We use the <literal>$wasCalled</literal>
      instance variable that is set by our implementation of
      <literal>update()</literal> to check whether the <literal>Subject</literal>
      object does what it is supposed to do:

<programlisting>public function testUpdate() {
    $subject = new Subject;
    $subject->attach($this);
    $subject->doSomething();

    $this->assertTrue($this->wasCalled);
}</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Notice that we create a new <literal>Subject</literal> object instead of
      relying on a global instance. Stubbing encourages this style of design.
      It reduces the coupling between objects and improves reuse.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you are not familiar with the self-shunt pattern, the tests can be
      hard to read. What is going on here? Why is a test case also an
      observer? Once you get used to the idiom, the tests are easy to read.
      Everything you need to understand the test is in one class.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
