<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<chapter id="database">
  <title>Database Testing</title>
  <para>
    Many beginner and intermediate unit testing examples in any programming
    language suggest that it is perfectly easy to test your application's logic with
    simple tests. For database-centric applications this is far away from the
    reality. Start using Wordpress, TYPO3 or Symfony with Doctrine or Propel,
    for example, and you will easily experience considerable problems with
    PHPUnit: just because the database is so tightly coupled to these libraries.
  </para>
  <para>
    You probably know this scenario from your daily work and projects,
    where you want to put your fresh or experienced PHPUnit skills to
    work and get stuck by one of the following problems:
  </para>
  <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The method you want to test executes a rather large JOIN operation and
        uses the data to calculate some important results.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Your business logic performs a mix of SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE and
        DELETE statements.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        You need to setup test data in (possibly much) more than two tables
        to get reasonable initial data for the methods you want to test.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    The DbUnit extension considerably simplifies the setup of a database for
    testing purposes and allows you to verify the contents of a database after
    performing a series of operations.
  </para>
  <section id="database.supported-vendors-for-database-testing">
    <title>Supported Vendors for Database Testing</title>
    <para>
      DbUnit currently supports MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle and SQLite. Through
      <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com">Zend Framework</ulink> or
      <ulink url="http://www.doctrine-project.org">Doctrine 2</ulink>
      integrations it has access to other database systems such as IBM DB2 or
      Microsoft SQL Server.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="database.difficulties-in-database-testing">
    <title>Difficulties in Database Testing</title>
    <para>
      There is a good reason why all the examples on unit testing do not include
      interactions with the database: these kind of tests are both complex to
      setup and maintain. While testing against your database you need to take
      care of the following variables:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The database schema and tables
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Inserting the rows required for the test into these tables
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Verifying the state of the database after your test has run
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Cleanup the database for each new test
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Because many database APIs such as PDO, MySQLi or OCI8 are cumbersome to
      use and verbose in writing doing these steps manually is an absolute
      nightmare.
    </para>
    <para>
      Test code should be as short and precise as possible for several reasons:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You do not want to modify considerable amount of test code for little
          changes in your production code.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You want to be able to read and understand the test code easily,
          even months after writing it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Additionally you have to realize that the database is essentially a
      global input variable to your code. Two tests in your test suite
      could run against the same database, possibly reusing data multiple
      times. Failures in one test can easily affect the result of the
      following tests making your testing experience very difficult. The
      previously mentioned cleanup step is of major importance
      to solve the <quote>database is a global input</quote> problem.
    </para>
    <para>
      DbUnit helps to simplify all these problems with database testing in an
      elegant way.
    </para>
    <para>
      What PHPUnit cannot help you with is the fact that database tests
      are very slow compared to tests not using the database. Depending
      on how large the interactions with your database are your tests
      could run a considerable amount of time. However if you keep the amount of
      data used for each test small and try to test as much code using
      non-database tests you can easily get away in under a minute even
      for large test suites.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <ulink url="http://www.doctrine-project.org">Doctrine 2
      project</ulink>'s test suite, for example, currently has a test suite of
      about 1000 tests where nearly half of them accesses the database
      and still runs in 15 seconds against a MySQL database on a standard
      desktop computer.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="database.the-four-stages-of-a-database-test">
    <title>The four stages of a database test</title>
    <para>
      In his book on xUnit Test Patterns Gerard Meszaros lists the four
      stages of a unit-test:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Set up fixture
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Exercise System Under Test
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Verify outcome
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Teardown
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">What is a Fixture?</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        A fixture describes the initial state your application and database
        are in when you execute a test.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      Testing the database requires you to hook into at least the
      setup and teardown to clean-up and write the required fixture data
      into your tables. However the database extension has good reason to
      revert the four stages in a database test to resemble the following
      workflow that is executed for each single test:
    </para>
    <section id="database.clean-up-database">
      <title>1. Clean-Up Database</title>
      <para>
        Since there is always a first test that runs against the database
        you do not know exactly if there is already data in the tables.
        PHPUnit will execute a TRUNCATE against all the tables you
        specified to reset their status to empty.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.set-up-fixture">
      <title>2. Set up fixture</title>
      <para>
        PHPUnit will then iterate over all the fixture rows specified and
        insert them into their respective tables.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.run-test-verify-outcome-and-teardown">
      <title>3–5. Run Test, Verify outcome and Teardown</title>
      <para>
        After the database is reset and loaded with its initial state the
        actual test is executed by PHPUnit. This part of the test code does
        not require awareness of the Database Extension at all, you can
        go on and test whatever you like with your code.
      </para>
      <para>
        In your test use a special assertion called
        <literal>assertDataSetsEqual()</literal> for verification purposes,
        however this is entirely optional. This feature will be explained
        in the section <quote>Database Assertions</quote>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="database.configuration-of-a-phpunit-database-testcase">
    <title>Configuration of a PHPUnit Database TestCase</title>
    <para>
      Usually when using PHPUnit your testcases would extend the
      <literal>PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase</literal> class in the
      following way:
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyTest extends PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase
{
    public function testCalculate()
    {
        $this->assertEquals(2, 1 + 1);
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
    <para>
      If you want to test code that works with the Database Extension the
      setup is a bit more complex and you have to extend a different
      abstract TestCase requiring you to implement two abstract methods
      <literal>getConnection()</literal> and
      <literal>getDataSet()</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyGuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    /**
     * @return PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection
     */
    public function getConnection()
    {
        $pdo = new PDO('sqlite::memory:');
        return $this->createDefaultDBConnection($pdo, ':memory:');
    }

    /**
     * @return PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_IDataSet
     */
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        return $this->createFlatXMLDataSet(dirname(__FILE__).'/_files/guestbook-seed.xml');
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
    <section id="database.implementing-getconnection">
      <title>Implementing getConnection()</title>
      <para>
        To allow the clean-up and fixture loading functionalities to work
        the PHPUnit Database Extension requires access to a database
        connection abstracted across vendors through the PDO library. It
        is important to note that your application does not need to be
        based on PDO to use PHPUnit's database extension, the connection is
        merely used for the clean-up and fixture setup.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the previous example we create an in-memory Sqlite connection
        and pass it to the <literal>createDefaultDBConnection</literal>
        method which wraps the PDO instance and the second parameter (the
        database-name) in a very simple abstraction layer for database
        connections of the type
        <literal>PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The section <quote>Using the Database Connection</quote> explains
        the API of this interface and how you can make the best use of it.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.implementing-getdataset">
      <title>Implementing getDataSet()</title>
      <para>
        The <literal>getDataSet()</literal> method defines how the initial
        state of the database should look before each test is
        executed. The state of a database is abstracted through the
        concepts DataSet and DataTable both being represented by the
        interfaces
        <literal>PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_IDataSet</literal> and
        <literal>PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_IDataTable</literal>.
        The next section will describe in detail how these concepts work
        and what the benefits are for using them in database testing.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the implementation we only need to know that the
        <literal>getDataSet()</literal> method is called once during
        <literal>setUp()</literal> to retrieve the fixture data-set and
        insert it into the database. In the example we are using a factory
        method <literal>createFlatXMLDataSet($filename)</literal> that
        represents a data-set through an XML representation.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.what-about-the-database-schema-ddl">
      <title>What about the Database Schema (DDL)?</title>
      <para>
        PHPUnit assumes that the database schema with all its tables,
        triggers, sequences and views is created before a test is run. This
        means you as developer have to make sure that the database is
        correctly setup before running the suite.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are several means to achieve this pre-condition to database
        testing.
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you are using a persistent database (not Sqlite Memory) you can
            easily setup the database once with tools such as phpMyAdmin for
            MySQL and re-use the database for every test-run.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you are using libraries such as
            <ulink url="http://www.doctrine-project.org">Doctrine 2</ulink> or
            <ulink url="http://www.propelorm.org/">Propel</ulink>
            you can use their APIs to create the database schema you
            need once before you run the tests. You can utilize
            <ulink url="http://www.phpunit.de/manual/current/en/textui.html">PHPUnit's Bootstrap and Configuration</ulink>
            capabilities to execute this code whenever your tests are run.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="database.tip-use-your-own-abstract-database-testcase">
      <title>Tip: Use your own Abstract Database TestCase</title>
      <para>
        From the previous implementation example you can easily see that
        <literal>getConnection()</literal> method is pretty static and
        could be re-used in different database test-cases. Additionally to
        keep performance of your tests good and database overhead low you
        can refactor the code a little bit to get a generic abstract test
        case for your application, which still allows you to specify a
        different data-fixture for each test case:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
abstract class MyApp_Tests_DatabaseTestCase extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    // only instantiate pdo once for test clean-up/fixture load
    static private $pdo = null;

    // only instantiate PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection once per test
    private $conn = null;

    final public function getConnection()
    {
        if ($this->conn === null) {
            if (self::$pdo == null) {
                self::$pdo = new PDO('sqlite::memory:');
            }
            $this->conn = $this->createDefaultDBConnection(self::$pdo, ':memory:');
        }

        return $this->conn;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        This has the database connection hardcoded in the PDO connection
        though. PHPUnit has another awesome feature that could make this
        testcase even more generic. If you use the
        <ulink url="http://www.phpunit.de/manual/current/en/appendixes.configuration.html#appendixes.configuration.php-ini-constants-variables">XML Configuration</ulink>
        you could make the database connection configurable per test-run.
        First let's create a <quote>phpunit.xml</quote> file in our tests/
        directory of the application that looks like:
      </para>
      <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<phpunit>
    <php>
        <var name="DB_DSN" value="mysql:dbname=myguestbook;host=localhost" />
        <var name="DB_USER" value="user" />
        <var name="DB_PASSWD" value="passwd" />
        <var name="DB_DBNAME" value="myguestbook" />
    </php>
</phpunit>
]]></screen>
      <para>
        We can now modify our test-case to look like:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
abstract class Generic_Tests_DatabaseTestCase extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    // only instantiate pdo once for test clean-up/fixture load
    static private $pdo = null;

    // only instantiate PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection once per test
    private $conn = null;

    final public function getConnection()
    {
        if ($this->conn === null) {
            if (self::$pdo == null) {
                self::$pdo = new PDO( $GLOBALS['DB_DSN'], $GLOBALS['DB_USER'], $GLOBALS['DB_PASSWD'] );
            }
            $this->conn = $this->createDefaultDBConnection(self::$pdo, $GLOBALS['DB_DBNAME']);
        }

        return $this->conn;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        We can now run the database test suite using different
        configurations from the command-line interface:
      </para>
      <screen><userinput>user@desktop> phpunit --configuration developer-a.xml MyTests/</userinput>
<userinput>user@desktop> phpunit --configuration developer-b.xml MyTests/</userinput></screen>
      <para>
        The possibility to run the database tests against different
        database targets easily is very important if you are developing on
        the development machine. If several developers run the database
        tests against the same database connection you can easily
        experience test-failures because of race-conditions.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="database.understanding-datasets-and-datatables">
    <title>Understanding DataSets and DataTables</title>
    <para>
      A central concept of PHPUnit's Database Extension are DataSets and
      DataTables. You should try to understand this simple concept to
      master database testing with PHPUnit. The DataSet and DataTable are
      an abstraction layer around your database tables, rows and
      columns. A simple API hides the underlying database contents in an
      object structure, which can also be implemented by other
      non-database sources.
    </para>
    <para>
      This abstraction is necessary to compare the actual contents of a
      database against the expected contents. Expectations can be
      represented as XML, YAML, CSV files or PHP array for example. The
      DataSet and DataTable interfaces enable the comparison of this
      conceptually different sources, emulating relational database
      storage in a semantically similar approach.
    </para>
    <para>
      A workflow for database assertions in your tests then consists of
      three simple steps:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specify one or more tables in your database by table name (actual
          dataset)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specify the expected dataset in your preferred format (YAML, XML,
          ..)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Assert that both dataset representations equal each other.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Assertions are not the only use-case for the DataSet and DataTable
      in PHPUnit's Database Extension. As shown in the previous section
      they also describe the initial contents of a database. You are
      forced to define a fixture dataset by the Database TestCase, which
      is then used to:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Delete all the rows from the tables specified in the dataset.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write all the rows in the data-tables into the database.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section id="database.available-implementations">
      <title>Available Implementations</title>
      <para>
        There are three different types of datasets/datatables:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            File-Based DataSets and DataTables
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Query-Based DataSet and DataTable
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Filter and Composition DataSets and DataTables
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The file-based datasets and tables are generally used for the
        initial fixture and to describe the expected state of the database.
      </para>
      <section id="database.flat-xml-dataset">
        <title>Flat XML DataSet</title>
        <para>
          The most common dataset is called Flat XML. It is a very simple xml
          format where a tag inside the root node
          <literal><![CDATA[<dataset>]]></literal> represents exactly one row in the
          database. The tags name equals the table to insert the row into and
          an attribute represents the column. An example for a simple guestbook
          application could look like this:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" created="2010-04-24 17:15:23" />
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" user="nancy" created="2010-04-26 12:14:20" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          This is obviously easy to write. Here
          <literal><![CDATA[<guestbook>]]></literal> is the table name where two rows
          are inserted into each with four columns <quote>id</quote>,
          <quote>content</quote>, <quote>user</quote> and
          <quote>created</quote> with their respective values.
        </para>
        <para>
          However this simplicity comes at a cost.
        </para>
        <para>
          From the previous example it isn't obvious how you would specify an
          empty table. You can insert a tag with no attributes with the name
          of the empty table. A flat xml file for an empty guestbook table
          would then look like:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          The handling of NULL values with the flat xml dataset is tedious. A
          NULL value is different than an empty string value in almost any
          database (Oracle being an exception), something that is difficult
          to describe in the flat xml format. You can represent a NULL's value
          by omitting the attribute from the row specification. If our
          guestbook would allow anonymous entries represented by a NULL value
          in the user column, a hypothetical state of the guestbook table
          could look like:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" created="2010-04-24 17:15:23" />
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" created="2010-04-26 12:14:20" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          In this case the second entry is posted anonymously. However this
          leads to a serious problem with column recognition. During dataset
          equality assertions each dataset has to specify what columns a
          table holds. If an attribute is NULL for all the rows of a
          data-table, how would the Database Extension know that the column
          should be part of the table?
        </para>
        <para>
          The flat xml dataset makes a crucial assumption now, defining that
          the attributes on the first defined row of a table define the
          columns of this table. In the previous example this would mean
          <quote>id</quote>, <quote>content</quote>, <quote>user</quote> and
          <quote>created</quote> are columns of the guestbook table. For the
          second row where <quote>user</quote> is not defined a NULL would be
          inserted into the database.
        </para>
        <para>
          When the first guestbook entry is deleted from the dataset only
          <quote>id</quote>, <quote>content</quote> and
          <quote>created</quote> would be columns of the guestbook table,
          since <quote>user</quote> is not specified.
        </para>
        <para>
          To use the Flat XML dataset effectively when NULL values are
          relevant the first row of each table must not contain any NULL
          value and only successive rows are allowed to omit attributes. This
          can be awkward, since the order of the rows is a relevant factor
          for database assertions.
        </para>
        <para>
          In turn, if you specify only a subset of the table columns in the
          Flat XML dataset all the omitted values are set to their default
          values. This will lead to errors if one of the omitted columns is
          defined as <quote>NOT NULL DEFAULT NULL</quote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          In conclusion I can only advise using the Flat XML datasets if you
          do not need NULL values.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can create a flat xml dataset instance from within your
          Database TestCase by calling the
          <literal>createFlatXmlDataSet($filename)</literal> method:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyTestCase extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        return $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('myFlatXmlFixture.xml');
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.xml-dataset">
        <title>XML DataSet</title>
        <para>
          There is another more structured XML dataset, which is a bit more
          verbose to write but avoids the NULL problems of the Flat XML
          dataset. Inside the root node <literal><![CDATA[<dataset>]]></literal> you
          can specify <literal><![CDATA[<table>]]></literal>,
          <literal><![CDATA[<column>]]></literal>, <literal><![CDATA[<row>]]></literal>,
          <literal><![CDATA[<value>]]></literal> and
          <literal><![CDATA[<null />]]></literal> tags. An equivalent dataset to the
          previously defined Guestbook Flat XML looks like:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <table name="guestbook">
        <column>id</column>
        <column>content</column>
        <column>user</column>
        <column>created</column>
        <row>
            <value>1</value>
            <value>Hello buddy!</value>
            <value>joe</value>
            <value>2010-04-24 17:15:23</value>
        </row>
        <row>
            <value>2</value>
            <value>I like it!</value>
            <null />
            <value>2010-04-26 12:14:20</value>
        </row>
    </table>
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          Any defined <literal><![CDATA[<table>]]></literal> has a name and requires
          a definition of all the columns with their names. It can contain zero
          or any positive number of nested <literal><![CDATA[<row>]]></literal>
          elements. Defining no <literal><![CDATA[<row>]]></literal> element means
          the table is empty. The <literal><![CDATA[<value>]]></literal> and
          <literal><![CDATA[<null />]]></literal> tags have to be specified in the
          order of the previously given <literal><![CDATA[<column>]]></literal>
          elements. The <literal><![CDATA[<null />]]></literal> tag obviously means
          that the value is NULL.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can create a xml dataset instance from within your
          Database TestCase by calling the
          <literal>createXmlDataSet($filename)</literal> method:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyTestCase extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        return $this->createXMLDataSet('myXmlFixture.xml');
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.mysql-xml-dataset">
        <title>MySQL XML DataSet</title>
        <para>
          This new XML format is specific to the
          <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com">MySQL database server</ulink>.
          Support for it was added in PHPUnit 3.5. Files in this format can
          be generated using the
          <ulink url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/mysqldump.html"><literal>mysqldump</literal></ulink>
          utility. Unlike CSV datasets, which <literal>mysqldump</literal>
          also supports, a single file in this XML format can contain data
          for multiple tables. You can create a file in this format by
          invoking <literal>mysqldump</literal> like so:
        </para>
        <screen><userinput>mysqldump --xml -t -u [username] --password=[password] [database] > /path/to/file.xml</userinput></screen>
        <para>
          This file can be used in your Database TestCase by calling the
          <literal>createMySQLXMLDataSet($filename)</literal> method:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyTestCase extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        return $this->createMySQLXMLDataSet('/path/to/file.xml');
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.yaml-dataset">
        <title>YAML DataSet</title>
        <para>
          Alternatively, you can use YAML dataset for the guestbook example:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
guestbook:
  -
    id: 1
    content: "Hello buddy!"
    user: "joe"
    created: 2010-04-24 17:15:23
  -
    id: 2
    content: "I like it!"
    user:
    created: 2010-04-26 12:14:20
]]></screen>
        <para>
          This is simple, convient AND it solves the NULL issue that the
          similar Flat XML dataset has. A NULL in YAML is just the column
          name without no value specified. An empty string is specified as
          <literal><![CDATA[column1: ""]]></literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The YAML Dataset has no factory method on the Database TestCase
          currently, so you have to instantiate it manually:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class YamlGuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    protected function getDataSet()
    {
        return new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_YamlDataSet(
            dirname(__FILE__)."/_files/guestbook.yml"
        );
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.csv-dataset">
        <title>CSV DataSet</title>
        <para>
          Another file-based dataset is based on CSV files. Each table of the
          dataset is represented as a single CSV file. For our guestbook
          example we would define a guestbook-table.csv file:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
id,content,user,created
1,"Hello buddy!","joe","2010-04-24 17:15:23"
2,"I like it!","nancy","2010-04-26 12:14:20"
]]></screen>
        <para>
          While this is very convenient for editing with Excel or OpenOffice,
          you cannot specify NULL values with the CSV dataset. An empty
          column will lead to the database default empty value being inserted
          into the column.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can create a CSV DataSet by calling:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class CsvGuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    protected function getDataSet()
    {
        $dataSet = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_CsvDataSet();
        $dataSet->addTable('guestbook', dirname(__FILE__)."/_files/guestbook.csv");
        return $dataSet;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.array-dataset">
        <title>Array DataSet</title>
        <para>
          There is no Array based DataSet in PHPUnit's Database Extension
          (yet), but we can implement our own easily. Our guestbook example
          should look like:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ArrayGuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    protected function getDataSet()
    {
        return new MyApp_DbUnit_ArrayDataSet(array(
            'guestbook' => array(
                array('id' => 1, 'content' => 'Hello buddy!', 'user' => 'joe', 'created' => '2010-04-24 17:15:23'),
                array('id' => 2, 'content' => 'I like it!',   'user' => null,  'created' => '2010-04-26 12:14:20'),
            ),
        ));
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          A PHP DataSet has obvious advantages over all the other file-based
          datasets:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              PHP Arrays can obviously handle <literal>NULL</literal> values.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You won't need additional files for assertions and can specify them
              directly in the TestCase.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          For this dataset like the Flat XML, CSV and YAML DataSets the keys
          of the first specified row define the table's column names, in the
          previous case this would be <quote>id</quote>,
          <quote>content</quote>, <quote>user</quote> and
          <quote>created</quote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The implementation for this Array DataSet is simple and
          straightforward:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MyApp_DbUnit_ArrayDataSet extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_AbstractDataSet
{
    /**
     * @var array
     */
    protected $tables = array();

    /**
     * @param array $data
     */
    public function __construct(array $data)
    {
        foreach ($data AS $tableName => $rows) {
            $columns = array();
            if (isset($rows[0])) {
                $columns = array_keys($rows[0]);
            }

            $metaData = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_DefaultTableMetaData($tableName, $columns);
            $table = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_DefaultTable($metaData);

            foreach ($rows AS $row) {
                $table->addRow($row);
            }
            $this->tables[$tableName] = $table;
        }
    }

    protected function createIterator($reverse = FALSE)
    {
        return new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_DefaultTableIterator($this->tables, $reverse);
    }

    public function getTable($tableName)
    {
        if (!isset($this->tables[$tableName])) {
            throw new InvalidArgumentException("$tableName is not a table in the current database.");
        }

        return $this->tables[$tableName];
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.query-sql-dataset">
        <title>Query (SQL) DataSet</title>
        <para>
          For database assertions you do not only need the file-based datasets
          but also a Query/SQL based Dataset that contains the actual
          contents of the database. This is where the Query DataSet shines:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
$ds = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_QueryDataSet($this->getConnection());
$ds->addTable('guestbook');
?>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          Adding a table just by name is an implicit way to define the
          data-table with the following query:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
$ds = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_QueryDataSet($this->getConnection());
$ds->addTable('guestbook', 'SELECT * FROM guestbook');
?>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          You can make use of this by specifying arbitrary queries for your
          tables, for example restricting rows, column or adding
          <literal>ORDER BY</literal> clauses:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
$ds = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_QueryDataSet($this->getConnection());
$ds->addTable('guestbook', 'SELECT id, content FROM guestbook ORDER BY created DESC');
?>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          The section on Database Assertions will show some more details on
          how to make use of the Query DataSet.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="database.database-db-dataset">
        <title>Database (DB) Dataset</title>
        <para>
          Accessing the Test Connection you can automatically create a
          DataSet that consists of all the tables with their content in the
          database specified as second parameter to the Connections Factory
          method.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can either create a dataset for the complete database as shown
          in <literal>testGuestbook()</literal>, or restrict it to a set of
          specified table names with a whitelist as shown in
          <literal>testFilteredGuestbook()</literal> method.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class MySqlGuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    /**
     * @return PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection
     */
    public function getConnection()
    {
        $database = 'my_database';
        $pdo = new PDO('mysql:...', $user, $password);
        return $this->createDefaultDBConnection($pdo, $database);
    }

    public function testGuestbook()
    {
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet();
        // ...
    }

    public function testFilteredGuestbook()
    {
        $tableNames = array('guestbook');
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet($tableNames);
        // ...
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.replacement-dataset">
        <title>Replacement DataSet</title>
        <para>
          I have been talking about NULL problems with the Flat XML and CSV
          DataSet, but there is a slightly complicated workaround to get both
          types of datasets working with NULLs.
        </para>
        <para>
          The Replacement DataSet is a decorator for an existing dataset and
          allows you to replace values in any column of the dataset by another
          replacement value. To get our guestbook example working with NULL
          values we specify the file like:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" created="2010-04-24 17:15:23" />
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" user="##NULL##" created="2010-04-26 12:14:20" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          We then wrap the Flat XML DataSet into a Replacement DataSet:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ReplacementTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        $ds = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('myFlatXmlFixture.xml');
        $rds = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_ReplacementDataSet($ds);
        $rds->addFullReplacement('##NULL##', null);
        return $rds;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="database.dataset-filter">
        <title>DataSet Filter</title>
        <para>
          If you have a large fixture file you can use the DataSet Filter for
          white- and blacklisting of tables and columns that should be
          contained in a sub-dataset. This is especially handy in combination
          with the DB DataSet to filter the columns of the datasets.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class DataSetFilterTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testIncludeFilteredGuestbook()
    {
        $tableNames = array('guestbook');
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet();

        $filterDataSet = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_DataSetFilter($dataSet);
        $filterDataSet->addIncludeTables(array('guestbook'));
        $filterDataSet->setIncludeColumnsForTable('guestbook', array('id', 'content'));
        // ..
    }

    public function testExcludeFilteredGuestbook()
    {
        $tableNames = array('guestbook');
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet();

        $filterDataSet = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_DataSetFilter($dataSet);
        $filterDataSet->addExcludeTables(array('foo', 'bar', 'baz')); // only keep the guestbook table!
        $filterDataSet->setExcludeColumnsForTable('guestbook', array('user', 'created'));
        // ..
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        <blockquote>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">NOTE</emphasis> You cannot use both exclude
            and include column filtering on the same table, only on different
            ones. Plus it is only possible to either white- or blacklist
            tables, not both of them.
          </para>
        </blockquote>
      </section>
      <section id="database.composite-dataset">
        <title>Composite DataSet</title>
        <para>
          The composite DataSet is very useful for aggregating several
          already existing datasets into a single dataset. When several
          datasets contain the same table the rows are appended in the
          specified order. For example if we have two datasets
          <emphasis>fixture1.xml</emphasis>:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" created="2010-04-24 17:15:23" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          and <emphasis>fixture2.xml</emphasis>:
        </para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" user="##NULL##" created="2010-04-26 12:14:20" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
        <para>
          Using the Composite DataSet we can aggregate both fixture files:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class CompositeTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function getDataSet()
    {
        $ds1 = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('fixture1.xml');
        $ds2 = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('fixture2.xml');

        $compositeDs = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_CompositeDataSet();
        $compositeDs->addDataSet($ds1);
        $compositeDs->addDataSet($ds2);

        return $compositeDs;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="database.beware-of-foreign-keys">
      <title>Beware of Foreign Keys</title>
      <para>
        During Fixture SetUp PHPUnit's Database Extension inserts the rows
        into the database in the order they are specified in your fixture.
        If your database schema uses foreign keys this means you have to
        specify the tables in an order that does not cause foreign key
        constraints to fail.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.implementing-your-own-datasetsdatatables">
      <title>Implementing your own DataSets/DataTables</title>
      <para>
        To understand the internals of DataSets and DataTables, lets have a
        look at the interface of a DataSet. You can skip this part if you
        do not plan to implement your own DataSet or DataTable.
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
interface PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_IDataSet extends IteratorAggregate
{
    public function getTableNames();
    public function getTableMetaData($tableName);
    public function getTable($tableName);
    public function assertEquals(PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_IDataSet $other);

    public function getReverseIterator();
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        The public interface is used internally by the
        <literal>assertDataSetsEqual()</literal> assertion on the Database
        TestCase to check for dataset quality. From the
        <literal>IteratorAggregate</literal> interface the IDataSet
        inherits the <literal>getIterator()</literal> method to iterate
        over all tables of the dataset. The reverse iterator allows PHPUnit to 
        truncate tables opposite the order they were created to satisfy foreign 
        key constraints.
      </para>
      <para>
        Depending on the implementation different approaches are taken to
        add table instances to a dataset. For example, tables are added
        internally during construction from the source file in all
        file-based datasets such as <literal>YamlDataSet</literal>,
        <literal>XmlDataSet</literal> or <literal>FlatXmlDataSet</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        A table is also represented by the following interface:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
interface PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_ITable
{
    public function getTableMetaData();
    public function getRowCount();
    public function getValue($row, $column);
    public function getRow($row);
    public function assertEquals(PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_ITable $other);
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        Except the <literal>getTableMetaData()</literal> method it is
        pretty self-explainatory. The methods are used are all required for
        the different assertions of the Database Extension that are
        explained in the next chapter. The
        <literal>getTableMetaData()</literal> method has to return an
        implementation of the
        <literal>PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_ITableMetaData</literal>
        interface, which describes the structure of the table. It holds
        information on:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The table name
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An array of column-names of the table, ordered by their appearance
            in the result-set.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An array of the primary-key columns.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        This interface also has an assertion that checks if two instances
        of Table Metadata equal each other, which is used by the data-set
        equality assertion.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="database.the-connection-api">
    <title>The Connection API</title>
    <para>
      There are three interesting methods on the Connection interface
      which has to be returned from the
      <literal>getConnection()</literal> method on the Database TestCase:
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
interface PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DB_IDatabaseConnection
{
    public function createDataSet(Array $tableNames = NULL);
    public function createQueryTable($resultName, $sql);
    public function getRowCount($tableName, $whereClause = NULL);

    // ...
}
?>]]></programlisting>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <literal>createDataSet()</literal> method creates a Database
          (DB) DataSet as described in the DataSet implementations section.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ConnectionTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testCreateDataSet()
    {
        $tableNames = array('guestbook');
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet();
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <literal>createQueryTable()</literal> method can be used to
          create instances of a QueryTable, give them a result name and SQL
          query. This is a handy method when it comes to result/table
          assertions as will be shown in the next section on the Database
          Assertions API.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ConnectionTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testCreateQueryTable()
    {
        $tableNames = array('guestbook');
        $queryTable = $this->getConnection()->createQueryTable('guestbook', 'SELECT * FROM guestbook');
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <literal>getRowCount()</literal> method is a convienent way to
          access the number of rows in a table, optionally filtered by an
          additional where clause. This can be used with a simple equality
          assertion:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ConnectionTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testGetRowCount()
    {
        $this->assertEquals(2, $this->getConnection()->getRowCount('guestbook'));
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="database.database-assertions-api">
    <title>Database Assertions API</title>
    <para>
      For a testing tool the Database Extension surely provides some
      assertions that you can use to verify the current state ot the
      database, tables and the row-count of tables. This section
      describes this functionality in detail:
    </para>
    <section id="database.asserting-the-row-count-of-a-table">
      <title>Asserting the Row-Count of a Table</title>
      <para>
        It is often helpful to check if a table contains a specific amount
        of rows. You can easily achieve this without additional glue code
        using the Connection API. Say we wanted to check that after
        insertion of a row into our guestbook we not only have the two
        initial entries that have accompanied us in all the previous
        example, but a third one:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class GuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testAddEntry()
    {
        $this->assertEquals(2, $this->getConnection()->getRowCount('guestbook'), "Pre-Condition");

        $guestbook = new Guestbook();
        $guestbook->addEntry("suzy", "Hello world!");

        $this->assertEquals(3, $this->getConnection()->getRowCount('guestbook'), "Inserting failed");
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="database.asserting-the-state-of-a-table">
      <title>Asserting the State of a Table</title>
      <para>
        The previous assertion is helpful, but we surely want to check the
        actual contents of the table to verify that all the values were
        written into the correct columns. This can be achieved by a table
        assertion.
      </para>
      <para>
        For this we would define a Query Table instance which derives its
        content from a table name and SQL query and compare it to a
        File/Array Based Data Set:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class GuestbookTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testAddEntry()
    {
        $guestbook = new Guestbook();
        $guestbook->addEntry("suzy", "Hello world!");

        $queryTable = $this->getConnection()->createQueryTable(
            'guestbook', 'SELECT * FROM guestbook'
        );
        $expectedTable = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet("expectedBook.xml")
                              ->getTable("guestbook");
        $this->assertTablesEqual($expectedTable, $queryTable);
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        Now we have to write the <emphasis>expectedBook.xml</emphasis> Flat
        XML file for this assertion:
      </para>
      <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" created="2010-04-24 17:15:23" />
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" user="nancy" created="2010-04-26 12:14:20" />
    <guestbook id="3" content="Hello world!" user="suzy" created="2010-05-01 21:47:08" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
      <para>
        This assertion would only pass on exactly one second of the
        universe though, on <emphasis>2010–05–01 21:47:08</emphasis>. Dates
        pose a special problem to database testing and we can circumvent
        the failure by omitting the <quote>created</quote> column from the
        assertion.
      </para>
      <para>
        The adjusted <emphasis>expectedBook.xml</emphasis> Flat XML file
        would probably have to look like the following to make the
        assertion pass:
      </para>
      <screen><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<dataset>
    <guestbook id="1" content="Hello buddy!" user="joe" />
    <guestbook id="2" content="I like it!" user="nancy" />
    <guestbook id="3" content="Hello world!" user="suzy" />
</dataset>
]]></screen>
      <para>
        We have to fix up the Query Table call:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
$queryTable = $this->getConnection()->createQueryTable(
    'guestbook', 'SELECT id, content, user FROM guestbook'
);
?>]]></programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="database.asserting-the-result-of-a-query">
      <title>Asserting the Result of a Query</title>
      <para>
        You can also assert the result of complex queries with the Query
        Table approach, just specify a result name with a query and
        compare it to a dataset:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class ComplexQueryTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testComplexQuery()
    {
        $queryTable = $this->getConnection()->createQueryTable(
            'myComplexQuery', 'SELECT complexQuery...'
        );
        $expectedTable = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet("complexQueryAssertion.xml")
                              ->getTable("myComplexQuery");
        $this->assertTablesEqual($expectedTable, $queryTable);
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="database.asserting-the-state-of-multiple-tables">
      <title>Asserting the State of Multiple Tables</title>
      <para>
        For sure you can assert the state of multiple tables at once and
        compare a query dataset against a file based dataset. There are two
        different ways for DataSet assertions.
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can use the Database (DB) DataSet from the Connection and
            compare it to a File-Based DataSet.
          </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class DataSetAssertionsTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testCreateDataSetAssertion()
    {
        $dataSet = $this->getConnection()->createDataSet(array('guestbook'));
        $expectedDataSet = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('guestbook.xml');
        $this->assertDataSetsEqual($expectedDataSet, $dataSet);
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can construct the DataSet on your own:
          </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
class DataSetAssertionsTest extends PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_TestCase
{
    public function testManualDataSetAssertion()
    {
        $dataSet = new PHPUnit_Extensions_Database_DataSet_QueryDataSet();
        $dataSet->addTable('guestbook', 'SELECT id, content, user FROM guestbook'); // additional tables
        $expectedDataSet = $this->createFlatXmlDataSet('guestbook.xml');

        $this->assertDataSetsEqual($expectedDataSet, $dataSet);
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="database.frequently-asked-questions">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <section id="database.will-phpunit-re-create-the-database-schema-for-each-test">
      <title>Will PHPUnit (re-)create the database schema for each
             test?</title>
      <para>
        No, PHPUnit requires all database objects to be available when the
        suite is started. The Database, tables, sequences, triggers and
        views have to be created before you run the test suite.
      </para>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.doctrine-project.org">Doctrine 2</ulink> or
        <ulink url="http://www.ezcomponents.org">eZ Components</ulink> have
        powerful tools that allows you to create the database schema from
        pre-defined datastructures, however these have to be hooked into
        the PHPUnit extension to allow automatic database re-creation
        before the complete test-suite is run.
      </para>
      <para>
        Since each test completely cleans the database you are not even
        required to re-create the database for each test-run. A permanently
        available database works perfectly.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.am-i-required-to-use-pdo-in-my-application-for-the-database-extension-to-work">
      <title>Am I required to use PDO in my application for the Database
             Extension to work?</title>
      <para>
        No, PDO is only required for the fixture clean- and set-up and for
        assertions. You can use whatever database abstraction you want
        inside your own code.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.what-can-i-do-when-i-get-a-too-much-connections-error">
      <title>What can I do, when I get a
             <quote>Too much Connections</quote> Error?</title>
      <para>
        If you do not cache the PDO instance that is created from the
        TestCase <literal>getConnection()</literal> method the number of
        connections to the database is increasing by one or more with each
        database test. With default configuration MySql only allows 100
        concurrent connections other vendors also have maximum connection
        limits.
      </para>
      <para>
        The SubSection
        <quote>Use your own Abstract Database TestCase</quote> shows how
        you can prevent this error from happening by using a single cached
        PDO instance in all your tests.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="database.how-to-handle-null-with-flat-xml-csv-datasets">
      <title>How to handle NULL with Flat XML / CSV Datasets?</title>
      <para>
        Do not do this. Instead, you should use either the XML or the YAML
        DataSets.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
