<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<chapter id="installation">
  <title>Installing PHPUnit</title>

  <section id="installation.requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      PHPUnit 3.7 requires PHP 5.3.3; using the latest version of PHP is highly
      recommended.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHPUnit requires the <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/ctype.installation.php">ctype</ulink>,
      <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/dom.setup.php">dom</ulink>, <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/json.installation.php">json</ulink>,
      <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/pcre.installation.php">pcre</ulink>,
      <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/reflection.installation.php">reflection</ulink>,
      and <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/spl.installation.php">spl</ulink>
      extensions. These extensions are usually compiled and enabled by default.
      Some of them cannot even be disabled and are therefore always available.
    </para>

    <para>
      For code coverage support, <ulink
      url="http://xdebug.org/">Xdebug</ulink> 2.1.3 is required; using the
      latest version of Xdebug is highly recommended. The <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/tokenizer.installation.php">tokenizer</ulink>
      extension is also required for the code coverage functionality to work.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <ulink
      url="http://php.net/manual/en/phar.installation.php">phar</ulink>
      extension is required for using PHPUnit from a PHP Archive (PHAR). You
      need to configure <literal>suhosin.executor.include.whitelist = phar</literal>
      if you are using the <ulink url="http://suhosin.org/">Suhosin</ulink>
      extension and would like to use PHPUnit from a PHP Archive (PHAR).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation.phar">
    <title>PHP Archive (PHAR)</title>

    <para>
      The easiest way to obtain PHPUnit is to download a <ulink
      url="http://php.net/phar">PHP Archive (PHAR)</ulink> that has all required
      (as well as some optional) dependencies of PHPUnit bundled in a single
      file:
    </para>

    <screen><userinput>wget https://phar.phpunit.de/phpunit.phar</userinput>
<userinput>chmod +x phpunit.phar</userinput>
<userinput>mv phpunit.phar /usr/local/bin/phpunit</userinput></screen>

    <note>
      <para>
        To download from <literal>https://phar.phpunit.de/</literal>  you need a
        client with <ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Server_Name_Indication">TLS/SNI
        support</ulink>, wget 1.14 (or later), for instance.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      You can also immediately use the PHAR after you have downloaded it, of
      course:
    </para>

    <screen><userinput>wget https://phar.phpunit.de/phpunit.phar</userinput>
<userinput>php phpunit.phar</userinput></screen>

    <section id="installation.phar.verification">
      <title>Verifying PHPUnit PHAR Releases</title>

      <para>
        All official releases of code distributed by the PHPUnit Project are
        signed by the release manager for the release. PGP signatures and SHA1
        hashes are available for verification on <ulink
        url="https://phar.phpunit.de/">phar.phpunit.de</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>
        The following example details how release verification works. We start
        by downloading <filename>phpunit.phar</filename> as well as its
        detached PGP signature <filename>phpunit.phar.asc</filename>:
      </para>

      <screen><userinput>wget https://phar.phpunit.de/phpunit.phar</userinput>
<userinput>wget https://phar.phpunit.de/phpunit.phar.asc</userinput></screen>

      <para>
        We want to verify PHPUnit's PHP Archive (<filename>phpunit.phar</filename>)
        against its detached signature (<filename>phpunit.phar.asc</filename>):
      </para>

      <screen><userinput>gpg phpunit.phar.asc</userinput>
gpg: Signature made Sat 19 Jul 2014 01:28:02 PM CEST using RSA key ID 6372C20A
gpg: Can't check signature: public key not found</screen>

      <para>
        We don't have the release manager's public key (<literal>6372C20A</literal>)
        in our local system. In order to proceed with the verification we need
        to retrieve the release manager's public key from a key server. One such
        server is <filename>pgp.uni-mainz.de</filename>. The public key servers
        are linked together, so you should be able to connect to any key server.
      </para>

      <screen><userinput>gpg --keyserver pgp.uni-mainz.de --recv-keys 0x4AA394086372C20A</userinput><![CDATA[
gpg: requesting key 6372C20A from hkp server pgp.uni-mainz.de
gpg: key 6372C20A: public key "Sebastian Bergmann <sb@sebastian-bergmann.de>" imported
gpg: Total number processed: 1
gpg:               imported: 1  (RSA: 1)]]></screen>

      <para>
        Now we have received a public key for an entity known as "Sebastian
        Bergmann &lt;sb@sebastian-bergmann.de&gt;". However, we have no way of
        verifying this key was created by the person known as Sebastian
        Bergmann. But, let's try to verify the release signature again.
      </para>

      <screen><userinput>gpg phpunit.phar.asc</userinput><![CDATA[
gpg: Signature made Sat 19 Jul 2014 01:28:02 PM CEST using RSA key ID 6372C20A
gpg: Good signature from "Sebastian Bergmann <sb@sebastian-bergmann.de>"
gpg:                 aka "Sebastian Bergmann <sebastian@php.net>"
gpg:                 aka "Sebastian Bergmann <sebastian@thephp.cc>"
gpg:                 aka "Sebastian Bergmann <sebastian@phpunit.de>"
gpg:                 aka "Sebastian Bergmann <sebastian.bergmann@thephp.cc>"
gpg:                 aka "[jpeg image of size 40635]"
gpg: WARNING: This key is not certified with a trusted signature!
gpg:          There is no indication that the signature belongs to the owner.
Primary key fingerprint: D840 6D0D 8294 7747 2937  7831 4AA3 9408 6372 C20A]]></screen>

      <para>
        At this point, the signature is good, but we don't trust this key. A
        good signature means that the file has not been tampered. However, due
        to the nature of public key cryptography, you need to additionally
        verify that key <literal>6372C20A</literal> was created by the real
        Sebastian Bergmann.
      </para>

      <para>
        Any attacker can create a public key and upload it to the public key
        servers. They can then create a malicious release signed by this fake
        key. Then, if you tried to verify the signature of this corrupt release,
        it would succeed because the key was not the "real" key. Therefore, you
        need to validate the authenticity of this key. Validating the
        authenticity of a public key, however, is outside the scope of this
        documentation.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="installation.composer">
    <title>Composer</title>

    <para>
      Simply add a dependency on <literal>phpunit/phpunit</literal> to your
      project's <literal>composer.json</literal> file if you use
      <ulink url="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</ulink> to manage the
      dependencies of your project. Here is a minimal example of a
      <literal>composer.json</literal> file that just defines a development-time
      dependency on PHPUnit 3.7:
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[{
    "require-dev": {
        "phpunit/phpunit": "3.7.*"
    }
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      For a system-wide installation via Composer, you can run:
    </para>

    <screen><userinput>composer global require "phpunit/phpunit=3.7.*"</userinput></screen>

    <para>
      Make sure you have <literal>~/.composer/vendor/bin/</literal> in your
      path.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Support for Composer and PHP Archive (PHAR) was added in PHPUnit 3.7
        (and is known to be stable since PHPUnit 3.7.5). Earlier releases of
        PHPUnit are not available through these distribution channels.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="installation.optional-packages">
    <title>Optional packages</title>

    <para>
      The following optional packages are available:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>PHP_Invoker</literal>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            A utility class for invoking callables with a timeout. This package is
            required to enforce test timeouts in strict mode.
          </para>

          <para>
            This package is included in the PHAR distribution of PHPUnit. It can
            be installed via Composer by adding the following
            <literal>"require-dev"</literal> dependency:
          </para>

          <screen><userinput>"phpunit/php-invoker": "*"</userinput></screen>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>DbUnit</literal>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            DbUnit port for PHP/PHPUnit to support database interaction testing.
          </para>

          <para>
            This package is included in the PHAR distribution of PHPUnit. It can
            be installed via Composer by adding the following
            <literal>"require-dev"</literal> dependency:
          </para>

          <screen><userinput>"phpunit/dbunit": ">=1.2"</userinput></screen>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>PHPUnit_Selenium</literal>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Selenium RC integration for PHPUnit.
          </para>

          <para>
            This package is included in the PHAR distribution of PHPUnit. It can
            be installed via Composer by adding the following
            <literal>"require-dev"</literal> dependency:
          </para>

          <screen><userinput>"phpunit/phpunit-selenium": ">=1.2"</userinput></screen>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="installing.upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading</title>

    <para>
      This section serves as a collection of minor BC issues that one might
      run into when upgrading from PHPUnit 3.6 to PHPUnit 3.7.
    </para>

    <para>
      The upgrade should be rather easy and work without any issues as it was
      tested against all major Open Source frameworks and there was not a
      single problem for them. Still every project is different and if you
      did not get around to trying one of the release candidates and have ran
      into an issue this document might provide some help.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">Removed deprecated OutputTestCase</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The class <literal>PHPUnit_Extensions_OutputTestCase</literal> has
            been removed. PHPUnit 3.6 issued a deprecation notice when it was
            used. To see how output can now be tested look into
            <xref linkend="writing-tests-for-phpunit.output" />.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">Current working directory will be restored after each test case</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If a test changes the current working directory
            (<literal>cwd</literal>) PHPUnit ran into issues when generating
            code coverage output. Now that the cwd is restored after each
            test case you might find that one of your tests depended on
            another test changing the cwd. Something that isn't desirable
            anyways and should be easy to fix.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">Test listeners trigger one autoload call</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When using custom test listeners as described in
            <xref linkend="appendixes.configuration.test-listeners"/> PHPUnit
            silently ignored missing test listeners and it was quite hard to
            debug that issues for the user. Now one autoload call will be
            triggered trying to locate the class. If your autoloader produces
            an error when it doesn't find a test listener you might run into an
            issue here. Removing the listener or making sure it's loaded in your
            <literal>bootstrap.php</literal> will solve this.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">Parameters for mock objects do not get cloned anymore</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Previously all object parameters where cloned when mocking.
            This lead to issues when testing trying to check whether the same
            object was passed to method or not and other problem with
            uncloneable objects. As a long standing feature request by many
            this behavior was changed.
            <xref linkend="test-doubles.mock-objects.examples.clone-object-parameters-usecase.php" />
            shows where the new implementation could be useful.
            <xref linkend="test-doubles.mock-objects.examples.enable-clone-object-parameters.php" />
            shows how to switch back to previous behavior.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">
          <literal>addUncoveredFilesFromWhitelist</literal>
          was removed in favor of
          <literal>processUncoveredFilesFromWhitelist</literal></emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When generating code coverage and using
            <literal><![CDATA[<whitelist addUncoveredFilesFromWhitelist="true">]]></literal>
            all uncovered files got included by PHPUnit. This was an issue for
            people with executable code in those files. PHPUnit will now scan
            the file and guess what code is executable and what code is not
            without including it. This might lead to different code coverage
            reports.
          </para>
          <para>
            To switch back to the old behavior the setting
            <literal><![CDATA[<whitelist processUncoveredFilesFromWhitelist="true">]]></literal>
            can be used. If you want the behavior with PHPUnit 3.6. and 3.7.
            it is possible to use both settings for a while.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">
          Default value of <literal>cacheTokens</literal> changed to
          <literal>false</literal></emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Since PHPUnit <literal>3.7.2</literal> we turned off the caching
            of tokenized files by default. When processing code coverage
            reports for big projects this cache consumed a lot of memory and
            due to the change in whitelist behavior it was problematic for
            folks with code bases with more than a couple of thousand classes.
          </para>
          <para>
            If your project is smaller or you have enough memory you will get
            a runtime benefit by adding <literal>cacheTokens="true"</literal>
            to your <literal>phpunit.xml</literal> file. See
            <xref linkend="appendixes.configuration.phpunit"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</chapter>
