<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<chapter id="strict-mode">
  <title>Strict Mode</title>

  <para>
    PHPUnit can perform additional checks while it executes the tests. In
    addition to the fine-grained control over the various strict mode checks
    (see below) you may use the <literal>--strict</literal> commandline option
    or set <literal>strict="true"</literal> in PHPUnit's XML configuration file
    to enable all of them.
  </para>

  <section id="strict-mode.useless-tests">
    <title>Useless Tests</title>

    <para>
      PHPUnit can be strict about tests that do not test anything. This check
      can be enabled by using the <literal>--report-useless-tests</literal>
      option on the commandline or by setting
      <literal>beStrictAboutTestsThatDoNotTestAnything="true"</literal> in
      PHPUnit's XML configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test that that does not perform an assertion will be marked as risky
      when this check is enabled. Expectations on mock objects or annotations
      such as <code>@expectedException</code> count as an assertion.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="strict-mode.unintentionally-covered-code">
    <title>Unintentionally Covered Code</title>

    <para>
      PHPUnit can be strict about unintentionally covered code. This check
      can be enabled by using the <literal>--strict-coverage</literal> option on
      the commandline or by setting
      <literal>checkForUnintentionallyCoveredCode="true"</literal> in PHPUnit's
      XML configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test that is annotated with <code>@covers</code> and executes code that
      is not listed using a <code>@covers</code> or <code>@uses</code>
      annotation will be marked as risky when this check is enabled.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="strict-mode.output-during-test-execution">
    <title>Output During Test Execution</title>

    <para>
      PHPUnit can be strict about output during tests. This check can be enabled
      by using the <literal>--disallow-test-output</literal> option on the
      commandline or by setting
      <literal>beStrictAboutOutputDuringTests="true"</literal> in PHPUnit's XML
      configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test that emits output, for instance by invoking <code>print</code> in
      either the test code or the tested code, will be marked as risky when this
      check is enabled.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="strict-mode.test-execution-timeout">
    <title>Test Execution Timeout</title>

    <para>
      A time limit can be enforced for the execution of a test if the
      <literal>PHP_Invoker</literal> package is installed and the
      <literal>pcntl</literal> extension is available. The enforcing of this
      time limit can be enabled by using the
      <literal>--enforce-time-limit</literal> option on the commandline or by
      setting <literal>beStrictAboutTestSize="true"</literal> in PHPUnit's XML
      configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test annotated with <literal>@large</literal> will fail if it takes
      longer than 60 seconds to execute. This timeout is configurable via the
      <literal>timeoutForLargeTests</literal> attribute in the XML
      configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test annotated with <literal>@medium</literal> will fail if it takes
      longer than 10 seconds to execute. This timeout is configurable via the
      <literal>timeoutForMediumTests</literal> attribute in the XML
      configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
      A test that is not annotated with <literal>@medium</literal> or
      <literal>@large</literal> will be treated as if it were annotated with
      <literal>@small</literal>. A small test will fail if it takes longer than
      1 second to execute. This timeout is configurable via the
      <literal>timeoutForSmallTests</literal> attribute in the XML configuration
      file.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

