<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<chapter id="testing-practices">
  <title>Testing Practices</title>

  <caution>
    <para>
      You are looking at the documentation for a version of PHPUnit that is no
      longer supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      The documentation for the current version of PHPUnit can be found
      <ulink url="../../current/en/index.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </caution>

  <blockquote>
    <attribution>Erich Gamma</attribution>
    <para>
      You can always write more tests. However, you will quickly find that
      only a fraction of the tests you can imagine are actually useful. What
      you want is to write tests that fail even though you think they should
      work, or tests that succeed even though you think they should fail.
      Another way to think of it is in cost/benefit terms. You want to write
      tests that will pay you back with information.
    </para>
  </blockquote>

  <section id="testing-practices.during-development">
    <title>During Development</title>

    <para>
      <indexterm><primary>Refactoring</primary></indexterm>

      When you need to make a change to the internal structure of the software
      you are working on to make it easier to understand and cheaper to modify
      without changing its observable behavior, a test suite is invaluable in
      applying these so called <ulink url="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/DefinitionOfRefactoring.html">refactorings</ulink>
      safely. Otherwise, you might not notice the system breaking while you
      are carrying out the restructuring.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following conditions will help you to improve the code and design
      of your project, while using unit tests to verify that the refactoring's
      transformation steps are, indeed, behavior-preserving and do not
      introduce errors:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>All unit tests run correctly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The code communicates its design principles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The code contains no redundancies.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The code contains the minimal number of classes and methods.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      When you need to add new functionality to the system, write the tests
      first. Then, you will be done developing when the test runs. This
      practice will be discussed in detail in the next chapter.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="testing-practices.during-debugging">
    <title>During Debugging</title>

    <para>
      When you get a defect report, your impulse might be to fix the defect as
      quickly as possible. Experience shows that this impulse will not serve
      you well; it is likely that the fix for the defect causes another
      defect.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can hold your impulse in check by doing the following:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Verify that you can reproduce the defect.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Find the smallest-scale demonstration of the defect in the code.
          For example, if a number appears incorrectly in an output, find the
          object that is computing that number.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write an automated test that fails now but will succeed when the
          defect is fixed.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Fix the defect.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      Finding the smallest reliable reproduction of the defect gives you the
      opportunity to really examine the cause of the defect. The test you
      write will improve the chances that when you fix the defect, you really
      fix it, because the new test reduces the likelihood of undoing the fix
      with future code changes. All the tests you wrote before reduce the
      likelihood of inadvertently causing a different problem.
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>Benjamin Smedberg</attribution>
      <para>
        Unit testing offers many advantages:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Testing gives code authors and reviewers confidence that patches produce the correct results.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Authoring testcases is a good impetus for developers to discover edge cases.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Testing provides a good way to catch regressions quickly, and to make sure that no regression will be repeated twice.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Unit tests provide working examples for how to use an API and can significantly aid documentation efforts.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Overall, integrated unit testing makes the cost and risk of any
        individual change smaller. It will allow the project to make [...]
        major architectural improvements [...] quickly and confidently.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
  </section>
</chapter>
